A Guide to the J. Sargeant Reynolds Papers, 1965-1991
Virginia Historical Society
Virginia Historical Society
A Guide to the J. Sargeant Reynolds Papers, 1965-1991
Virginia Historical Society
Mss1 R2265 a FA2
1,800 items (18 manuscript boxes).
Include public correspondence, press releases, speeches, newspaper clippings, printed materials, legislative bills, private writings, condolences, and family correspondence relating to the political career of J. Sargeant Reynolds, member of the Virginia House of Delegates and Senate, who served as Lieutenant Governor until untimely his death in 1971.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Mrs. Mary Ballou Reynolds Ballentine, Richmond, Va., in 1994.
Biographical/Historical Information
Julian Sargeant Reynolds was born June 30, 1936 in New York City moved in 1938 to Richmond with his parents, Mr. and Mrs. Richard Samuel Reynolds, Jr. Mr. R. S. Reynolds of the Reynolds Metals Company was President from 1948-63 and became CEO in 1963. Julian Sargeant Reynolds attended Woodberry Forest School in Orange, Virginia, and the Wharton School of Finance at the University of Pennsylvania where he graduated with a Bachelor of Science degree in Economics in 1958. He joined the Reynolds Metals Company and worked in the Market Research Department until 1959. He later worked with the Corporate Planning Department until 1961 leaving to become the companies assistant treasurer. In January, 1965, he was elected Executive Vice President of Reynolds Aluminum Credit Corporation. In 1964 he was elected to the House of Delegates from the Richmond and Henrico County district. He served in the House until his election to the 13th senatorial (Richmond and Henrico) district of the Virginia General Assembly. He resigned from the senate in 1969 to serve as the elected lieutenant governor of Virginia from 1970 until his death June 13, 1971. Julian Sargeant Reynolds was married twice. The first marriage was performed in Hertford, N. C., September 29, 1956 to Elizabeth Weir Veeneman of Louisville, Kentucky. The couple had three children, Virginia Weir, J. Sargeant, and Jeanne Elizabeth. The couple divorced in 1969. His second marriage was to the former Mary Ballou Handy of Lynchburg, Va., in 1969. By his second marriage he had one son, Richard Roland.
Scope and Content Information
This collection has been divided into thirty seven (37) series that are primarily organized to coincide with the political life of Reynolds. Series One contains information pertaining to Reynold's successful bid for a seat in the Virginia House of Delegates. Series Two includes correspondence, clippings and press releases from 1966 while in the House of Delegates. Series Three contains correspondence, committee work which includes the proposed merger of the Medical College of Virginia and Richmond Professional Institute, and the proposed consolidation of Richmond and Henrico county.
Series Four include campaign materials from the November 7, 1967 Virginia Senate race. Series Five includes senate correspondence, speeches given as senator. Series Six contains information on Virginia Senate bills and correspondence pertaining to senate legislation. Series Seven contains press release and letters to colleagues announcing his run for lieutenant governor, and resignation from the senate.
Series Eight contains campaign material concerning his election as lieutenant governor. Series Nine contains information pertaining to the expenses associated with running for the office of lieutenant governor. Series Ten contains congratulatory correspondence on a successful lieutenant governors race. Series Eleven includes materials concerning the inauguration of A. Linwood Holton (as governor) and Reynolds as lieutenant governor. Series Twelve includes correspondence and information of the proposed 1969 constitution change in Virginia. Series Thirteen includes materials pertaining to Virginia's POW's in Viet Nam, while he is lieutenant governor. Series Fourteen includes correspondence with the Federation of Women's Club, and initiatives to improve medical services in Virginia. Series Fifteen contains information on commission appointment while Reynolds served as lieutenant governor. Series Sixteen includes correspondence, clippings, and press release while Reynolds was lieutenant governor.
Series Seventeen contains speeches correspondence and clippings of Reynolds involvement with the Young Democratic Club of Virginia. Series Eighteen contains speeches correspondence and clippings of Reynolds involvement with the Jaycees Civic Association of Virginia. Series Nineteen contains correspondences speeches made at Virginia colleges. Series Twenty includes Reynolds correspondence to various groups events and organizations.
Series Twenty-one contains information correspondence, and speech given at the annual Shad Plank gathering in Southside Virginia. Series Twenty-two contains information on Reynolds involvement with the Richmond Urban League. Series Twenty-three contains speeches correspondence and clippings pertaining to Reynolds association with the Virginia Easter Seals Society. Series Twenty-four include speeches and correspondence pertaining to the Model General Assembly. Series Twenty-five contains general correspondence, press releases speeches and clippings (arranged chronologically) from 1961-1971. Series Twenty-six includes speeches and correspondence concerning high school speeches (1964-1971).
Series Twenty-seven contains clippings, correspondence and press release concerning the medical condition of Reynolds. Series Twenty-eight includes clippings, condolences press releases, and funeral arrangements, pertaining to the death of Reynolds, June 13, 1971. Series Twenty-nine includes contracts, and correspondence concerning the portrait dedication to commemorate the late lieutenant governor.
Series Thirty contains information concerning the creation and dedication of J. Sargeant Reynolds Community College. Series Thirty-one contains press release, correspondence and clippings pertaining to the opening of the Reynold's homestead in Patrick County.
Series Thirty-two contains biographies and chronologies pertaining to the life of Reynolds. Series Thirty-three includes correspondence and clippings relating to first wife Virginia Weir and children. Series Thirty-four includes correspondence and clippings relating to second wife Mary Ballou. Series Thirty five includes personal correspondence of Reynolds and Virginia Governor A. Linwood Holton, Jr. Series Thirty-six includes personal correspondence of Mrs. R.S. Reynolds (mother of Julian Sargeant Reynolds).
The final series 37 is a compilation of miscellaneous information not able to easily fit in the categories listed above.
Organization
This collection is arranged primary in chronological order with only a few exceptions. Each series in then broken into individual folders organized with similar items sharing the same folder. The collection begins with Julian Sargeant Reynold's political life as a member of the Virginia House of Delegates. Julian Sargeant Reynolds was a delegate from the Richmond and Henrico County District. He served in the house of delegates from 1964-1966 [Series 1-3].
The next stage of the political life of Reynolds was his tenure in the Virginia senate. Reynolds served in senatorial district #13 from 1967-1969, before leaving to become the lieutenant governor of Virginia. Julian Sargeant Reynold resigned from the senate on November 12, 1969 to accept the office of lieutenant governor. [Series 4-7] (with series seven concerned with the lieutenant governor campaign while in the senate).
Julian Sargeant Reynolds served as lieutenant governor from 1970 until his death, June 13, 1971. These series span the entire length of Julian Sargeant Reynolds career as the lieutenant governor of Virginia. [Series 8-24]
Series 25-26 are the only series that encompass the entire span of Reynolds public life with out respect to the office he was occupying. Series 25 runs from 1961-1971. While section 26 includes speech and correspondence from 1964-1971. These two series cover the entire span of the collection, with correspondences, press releases and clippings.
The next grouping series 27-28 consist primarily of papers discussing the illness, subsequent death, of Julian Sargeant Reynolds. Materials maintained by other members of the family are included in these series.
Index Terms
Democratic Party (Va.) -- History -- 20th century.; Elections -- Virginia -- History -- 20th century.; Henrico County (Va.) -- Politics and government, 1951-; Holton, A. Linwood (Abner Linwood), 1923-; Mentally ill -- Care -- Virginia -- History -- 20th century.; Reynolds, J. Sargeant (Julian Sargeant), 1936-1971.; Richmond (Va.) -- Politics and government -- 1951-; Vietnamise Conflict, 1961-1975 -- Prisoners and prisons.; Virginia -- Politics and government -- 1951-; Virginia. Commission to Plan for the Establishment of a Proposed State-supported University in the Richmond Metropolitan Area.; Virginia. Constitution (1972); Virginia. General Assembly -- Members -- History -- 20th century.; Virginia. Governor (1970-1974: Holton); Virginia. Lieutenant Governor (1970-1971: Reynolds)
Contents List
- Virginia House of Delegates Campaign.
  Press releases, correspondence, campaign advertisements, and newspaper clippings concerning Reynolds's campaign for the Virginia House of Delegates.
  - Press releases.
  - Correspondence.
  - Congratulatory telegram from Richard S. Reynolds.
  - Campaign advertisements.
  - Newspaper clippings.
- Virginia House of Delegates materials, 1966. (Box 1 (cont.))
  General correspondence, newspaper clippings, and press releases 1966, concerning Julian Sargeant Reynold's service as a member of the Virginia House of Delegates.
  - Correspondence, January-February 1966.
  - Correspondence, March-April 1966.
  - Correspondence, May-June 1966.
  - Correspondence, July-August 1966.
  - Correspondence, September-October 1966.
  - Correspondence, November-December 1966.
  - Newspaper clippings.
- House of Delegates Committee materials. (Box 2)
  Contains clippings, correspondence, minutes, and committee working files involving Julian Sargeant Reynolds while a member of the Virginia House of Delegates. Committee work includes consolidation of Richmond Professional Institute and Medical College of Virginia into Virginia Commonwealth University, and the proposed consolidation of Richmond and Henrico County.
  - Correspondence on proposed merger between Richmond and Henrico County.
  - Press release on merger between Richmond and Henrico.
  - Resolution by Henrico County Board of Supervisors.
  - Speeches about merger between Richmond and Henrico County.
  - Newspaper clippings about merger between Richmond and Henrico County.
  - Mental Health Care in Virginia.
  - Position on mentally ill taken by the Democratic candidates.
  - Speech on Virginia mental health care.
  - Press release on mental health care.
  - Correspondence on mental health care.
  - Newspaper clippings on mental health care.
  - Oath of the Commission to Plan the Establishment of a New State University in the Richmond Metropolitan Area.
  - Report of the Commission to Plan for the Establishment of a New State University in the Richmond Metropolitan Area.
  - Site evaluation for a Metropolitan Richmond University.
  - Appointment certificate.
  - Minutes of the second meeting, 28 September 1966.
  - Correspondence, 1966.
  - Correspondence, 1967.
  - Correspondence, 1968.
  - Memoranda.
  - Newspaper clippings.
- Virginia Senate Campaign. (Box 3)
  Materials containing information on the Virginia Senate race of Julian Sargeant Reynolds. Include votes cast, advertisements, candidacy announcement, clippings, endorsements, press releases, and radio spots.
  - Statement of votes cast in 7 November 1967 election.
  - Campaign advertisements.
  - Announcement of candidacy.
  - Endorsements.
  - Press releases.
  - Radio spot.
  - Newspaper clippings.
- Virginia Senate Materials. (Box 3 (cont.))
  Correspondence, 1968, of Julian Sergeant Reynolds (as a Virginia State senator) also include speeches and his resignation from the Senate to run for lieutenant governor of Virginia.
  - Senate speeches, 1968.
  - Resignation from Senate.
  - Announcement of candidacy.
  - Senate prayer.
  - Thank you letters from groups visiting the State Capitol.
  - Democratic State Convention press release and clippings.
  - Blank Senate stationary.
  - Newspaper clippings, 1968.
- Virginia Senate bills, support materials, 1968-1969. (Box 4)
  Information on Virginia Senate bills, including the small loan act, right to work, and housing matters. Also, include correspondence, clippings, and speeches of Julian Sargeant Reynolds as a Virginia State Senator relating to these topics.
  - Memo on Small Loan Act (1968).
  - Correspondence, Right to Work bill.
  - Housing bill, draft.
  - Housing bill, correspondence.
  - Housing bill, memo.
  - Housing bill, clippings.
  - Housing bill, miscellaneous.
  - Handicapped children education (S.B.458).
  - Habitual offender (S.B. 77), 1968.
  - Drug Bill, text.
  - Drug Bill, correspondence.
  - Drug Bill, clippings.
  - Drug Bill, speech.
  - Emergency Committee on Social Problems in Richmond.
  - Alcohol Bill (1968).
  - Commission to study the formula for aide to public school.
  - Abortion correspondence.
  - Insurance matters (S.B. 256).
  - Interest rate correspondence.
  - Kindergarten program correspondence, 1968.
  - James River legislation.
  - General Assembly legislation, misc., 1968-1969.
  - Senate correspondence, January 1968.
  - Senate correspondence, February 1968.
  - Senate correspondence, March-September 1968.
  - Senate correspondence, 1969.
  - Miscellaneous.
- Virginia Lieutenant Governor campaign. (Box 5)
  Contains press releases, speeches, and clippings. Also correspondence of Julian Sergeant Reynolds with U.S. congressional and Virginia legislators announcing his candidacy for Lieutenant Governor of Virginia.
  - Letters announcing candidacy to U.S. Congress.
  - Letters announcing candidacy to Virginia Senate.
  - Letters announcing candidacy to Virginia House of Delegates.
  - Statement of candidacy, press release.
  - Statement of candidacy, speeches.
  - Statement of candidacy to various people.
  - Clippings.
  - Telegrams.
  - Campaign correspondence.
- Virginia Lieutenant Governor campaign miscellany. (Box 5 (cont.))
  Materials concerning the election and campaign of Julian Sergeant Reynolds for lieutenant governor of Virginia. Include bumper stickers, broadsides, letters of support, clippings, results, advertising, campaign speeches of Julian Sargeant Reynolds.
  - Letters of support, 1969.
  - Thank yous for support.
  - Election results, 1969.
  - Campaign speeches, 1969.
  - Bumper stickers, button.
  - Campaign advertising.
  - Clippings.
- Virginia Lieutenant Governor campaign expenses. (Box 6)
  Records of campaign expenses, and expense sheets from Audio Fidelity Broadcast Corp., and Evert Waddey printing company. Also, include correspondence concerning hotels, food, printed materials, phone bills and all general expenses associated with Julian Sargeant Reynold's run for the office of lieutenant governor.
  - Audio Fidelity correspondence and bills.
  - Everett Waddey correspondence and bills.
  - Xerox Corporation correspondence and bills.
  - Campaign expense sheets.
  - Campaign expenses, hotels.
  - Campaign expenses, food.
  - Campaign expenses, printed materials.
  - Campaign expenses, beverages.
  - Campaign expenses, photography.
  - Campaign expenses, flowers.
  - Campaign expenses, phone bills.
  - Campaign expenses, billboards.
  - Campaign expenses, office supplies.
  - Campaign expenses, freight.
  - Campaign expenses, miscellaneous.
- Virginia Lieutenant Governor campaign congratulatory correspondence. (Box 7)
  Contains congratulatory correspondence from Thalhimer Brothers, U.S. congressmen, Virginia lawmakers, colleges, labor unions, public and private citizens to Julian Sergeant Reynolds on a 1969 successful lieutenant governors race.
  - Thalhimers Bros.
  - U.S. Congress.
  - Virginia Senate.
  - Virginia House of Delegates.
  - Virginia state agencies.
  - Virginia colleges.
  - Labor unions.
  - Law offices.
  - Judicial agencies.
  - Local governments.
  - Personal acquaintances.
  - General public.
  - Telegrams.
- Virginia Gubernatorial Inauguration, 1970. (Box 7 (cont.))
  - Tickets, correspondence, schedule of events.
  - Program book for the Inaugural Ceremonies, 17 January 1970.
- Virginia Constitution changes, proposed. (Box 8)
  Includes correspondence, proposals and information on the 1969-1970 proposed constitutional change in Virginia.
  - Correspondence, Governor Holton.
  - Correspondence, 1969.
  - Correspondence, 1970-1971.
- Prisoners of War Action Committee. (Box 8 (cont.))
  Correspondence of Julian Sargeant Reynolds (as lieutenant governor of Virginia) about Virginians held as Prisoners of War in Viet Nam. Includes materials from the POW Action Committee, Argus advertising, and information relating to POW-MIA initiatives.
  - POW Action Committee.
  - Argus Advertising.
  - Correspondence, Mrs. Phyllis E. Galanti.
  - Speech.
  - Correspondence, 1970-1971.
- Federation of Women's Club and the Virginia Mental Health Initiative. (Box 8 (cont.))
  Includes correspondence of Julian Sargeant Reynolds (as lieutenant governor of Virginia) concerning the Federation of Women's Club, and initiatives to improve medical and mental health services in Virginia.
  - Virginia Federation of Women Clubs.
  - Virginia Mental Health Research and Education Foundation, 1970-1971.
  - Resolution and articles of incorporation.
  - Carton Industries correspondence.
  - Cancer research bills.
- Commission appointments (Box 8 (cont.))
  Includes information on commission appointments to and from Julian Sargeant Reynolds (as lieutenant governor of Virginia). Also, includes information a on commission to study para-mutual betting and general legislative committee matters.
  - Para-mutual commission, 1971
  - Various commission appointments.
  - Miscellaneous.
- Correspondence, clippings and press releases, 1970-1971. (Box 9)
  Includes correspondence, clippings, and press releases of Julian Sargeant Reynolds (as lieutenant governor of Virginia) from 1970-1971. Correspondence, clippings and press releases, 1970-1971. Among Reynolds's accomplishments was the appointment of the first female page to the Virginia General Assembly.
  - Thompson, W. Carrington, Resignation of.
  - Thank you trooper rides.
  - Dawbarn, H. "Buz".
  - Godwin, Miles E.
  - Holton, A. Linwood, Jr.
  - "Reynolds Wrap Affair."
  - WCVE
  - Muskie, Ed.
  - Correspondence with media.
  - Law Day, 1970.
  - Female page appointment.
  - Health issues, 1970.
  - Industrial development.
  - College campus issues.
  - Party for Virginia state senators 1970.
  - Naturalization Ceremonies, 19 February 1971.
  - Central State Hospital.
  - Speeches, 1970.
  - Correspondence, undated.
  - Correspondence, 1970.
  - Correspondence, 1971.
  - Press releases, undated.
  - Press releases, 1970.
  - Press releases, 1971.
  - Clippings, 1970.
  - Clippings, 1971.
  - Miscellaneous information.
- Young Democratic Club of Virginia. (Box 10)
  Contains speeches, correspondence and clippings concerning Julian Sargeant Reynold's involvement with the Young Democratic Club of Virginia.
  - Correspondence.
  - Financial materials.
  - Publications.
  - Speeches and press releases.
  - Clippings.
- Jaycees Civic Association of Virginia. (Box 10 (cont.))
  Contains speeches, correspondence, and clippings concerning Julian Sargeant Reynolds involvement with the Jaycees Civic Association of Virginia.
  - West End Jaycees (Richmond and Henrico County).
  - Congratulations, Virginia Outstanding Young Men.
  - Application, "Ten Outstanding Young Men".
  - "New Dominion" (official publication of the Virginia Jaycees) and "Commonwealth Magazine" articles.
  - Correspondence.
- University and college speaking engagements. (Box 10 (cont.))
  Includes Julian Sargeant Reynold's correspondence concerning and speeches made at college ceremonies in Virginia.
  - University of Richmond.
  - Virginia State College.
  - Virginia Military Institute.
  - Sullins College (Bristol, Va.).
- Civic and Labor Groups and Events. (Box 11)
  Includes general correspondence of Julian Sargeant Reynolds concerning various groups, events, and organizations.
  - Young Citizens for Johnson and Humphrey.
  - AFL-CIO.
  - Kiwanis.
  - Jefferson and Jackson Day.
  - Norfolk Walk Committee, April 1971.
  - County of Fairfax.
  - Democratic National Committee dinner.
  - Friends Association for Children.
  - United Way ground breaking, 7 April 1971.
  - Daughters of the American Revolution.
  - Black is Beautiful Business Exposition.
  - Salvation Army.
  - Anti-Defamation League.
  - Independence Day at Monticello.
  - Tidewater Association of Home Builders.
  - Rotary Club.
  - Humanitarian Awards, 21 March 1971.
  - Young Mens Christian Association.
  - Exchange Club.
  - National Association of Homes for Boys.
  - Middle States Apprentice Training Conference.
  - Junior Women's Club.
  - Richmond Personnel and Guidance Association.
  - Virginia School Equipment Company.
  - Retired Teachers Association.
  - Jewish Community Center.
  - Board of Christian Education.
  - Boys' State.
  - Legionaires.
  - Orientation Institute for Foreign Students.
  - Miscellaneous.
- Shad Planking, 1971. (Box 12)
  Contains information, correspondence, speech, and response to the 21 April 1971 speech of Julian Sargeant Reynolds (as lieutenant governor) at the annual Shad Plank gathering in Southside Virginia. Reynold's speech attacked the right-wing practice of Massive Resistance on civil rights.
  - Correspondence.
  - Speech.
  - Reaction against speech.
  - Letters of support.
  - Response from Julian Sergeant Reynolds.
  - Clippings.
- Richmond Urban League. (Box 12 (cont.))
  Contains speeches, correspondence, and clippings concerning Julian Sargeant Reynolds, involvement with the Richmond Urban League.
  - Correspondence.
  - Annual report, 1971.
  - Speeches.
  - Press releases and clippings.
- Virginia Easter Seals Society. (Box 12 (cont.))
  Contains speeches, correspondence, and clippings concerning Julian Sargeant Reynolds involvement with the Virginia Easter Seals Society.
  - Correspondence.
  - Speeches.
  - Press releases and printed materials.
- Model General Assembly. (Box 13)
  Include speeches and correspondence of Julian Sergeant Reynolds concerning the Model General Assembly.
  - Correspondence.
  - Speeches.
- General publicity and Miscellany. (Box 13 (cont.))
  Contains general correspondence, press releases, speeches, and newspaper clippings (arranged chronologically) of Julian Sargeant Reynolds from 1961-1971.
  - Press releases, 1961.
  - Correspondence, 1964.
  - Speeches, 1964.
  - Press releases, 1964.
  - Clippings, 1964.
  - Miscellaneous, 1964.
  - Correspondence, 1965.
  - Press releases, 1965.
  - Speeches, 1965.
  - Correspondence, 1966.
  - Speeches, 1966.
  - Correspondence, 1967.
  - Clippings, 1967.
  - Correspondence, 1969 (January-March).
  - Correspondence, 1969 (April-July).
  - Correspondence, 1969 (August-December).
  - Telegram, 1969.
  - Bills, 1969.
  - Speeches, 1970.
  - Speeches, 1971.
  - Speeches, undated.
- High School Commencement materials. (Box 14)
  Includes speeches and correspondence [1964-1971] concerning high school commencement ceremonies of Julian Sargeant Reynolds.
  - Hermitage High School, 22 October 1964.
  - J. R. Tucker High School, 10 June 1966.
  - Robert E. Lee School (Springfield, Va.), 7 June 1970.
  - Manchester High School, 10 June 1970.